Bessie Alva Griffiths Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Bessie Alva Griffiths Papers
1888-1940
Griffiths, Bessie
Houston pianist Bessie Alva Griffiths studied piano with local philanthropist Ima Hogg before going on to give recitals and to teach piano in her home. Griffith's papers include personal photographs, some programs and other materials related to her career, and a small amount of memorabilia.
2 boxes, 1 oversize folder; 1 linear feet
1969-020
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Biographical Note
Native Houstonian Bessie Griffiths was born in 1896. She studied piano with Ima Hogg, the daughter of former governer James Hogg, who gave music lessons to a select group of students before going on to become a leading local art patron. Between 1912 and 1916 Griffiths studied with various teachers in Europe. After her return to Houston, Griffiths performed with the Houston Symphony, gave recitals accompanied by her sister Florence, and taught piano at a studio that she maintained in her home. Griffiths died some time after 1971.
Scope and Contents
The Bessie Alva Griffiths Collection contains photographs, memorabilia, and papers such as programs and miscellaneous correspondence and receipts. The dates of items in the collection range from 1888-1940. Original order of materials has been adhered to whenever possible. Correspondence and receipts are arranged in chronological order.
Included among the papers in the Griffiths Collection are materials belonging to Griffiths' roommate Katherine Dick, who may have been associated with the Harris County School for Girls, and a manuscript which may have been written by Bessie Griffiths.
Subjects (Persons)
Griffiths, Bessie Alva, b. 1896; Hogg, Ima
Formats
Programs; Photographs; Correspondence
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Detailed Description
- Photographs (Box 1, Folder 1-67)
  Photographs in the collection date primarily from the 19th century, and include photographs in the carte de visite and cabinet card formats, and tintypes. Many of the photographs were removed from their original housing for preservation purposes. Photographs in folders 1-11 were removed from envelopes, photographs in folders 12-21, folders 22-36, and folders 42-67 were removed from three different albums. Original order has been maintained, and descriptive information such as names has been noted in the folder listing below. Folders 37-41 contain miscellaneous materials such as newspaper clippings and handwritten prayers which were removed from the second photograph album.
  - Unidentified, before 1900 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
  - Related to Cornelia Ennis Cargill College, ca. 1920 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Harris County School for Girls, Bellaire, Texas, ca. 1920 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Unidentified, before 1900 (Box 1, Folder 10-18)
  - Unidentified, before 1900, "Miss Lou O'Banion of San Marcos, Texas 440 lbs," April 20, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Unidentified, before 1900 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Charles W. Crouch, Mr. and Mrs. Crouch, unidentified, before 1900 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Willie H. Crouch, J.D. Crouch, Mrs. Mary Holman, before 1900 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - I.S. Crouch, [Robert Russell?], before 1900 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Mrs. Kati Cherry, Miss Cora Cherry, Mr. J. Burleson, before 1900 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Miss Victoria Thomas, C.I. Polk, before 1900 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Mrs. Mary Massiv, [Henry Russell?], before 1900 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - [--] Hopkins, Willie H. Crouch, Lottie Cruger, Helen Cruger, before 1900 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Willie Massin, unidentified, Mrs. V. Polk, before 1900 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Jack King, Katie King, J.D. King, before 1900 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - J.V. Polk, Henry K. Polk, James Polk, before 1900 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Bormond Cruger, Helen Cruger, Sam H. King, before 1900 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Lenny Dunn, Mag. Cane, Laura Cane, before 1900 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Marie Crouch, Marie Massin, before 1900, Flory (Inscribed on back, "Dear old Per. from your loving sister Flory, September 1889") (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Unidentified, Brantly and Julia, before 1900 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Unidentified, before 1900 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Bessie Griffith Studio, ca. 1940 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Unidentified; newspaper clipping: Leslie Spots, 1958-1965 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Unidentified, ca. 1920 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Newspaper clippings: Jan Robinson, Forest Peterson, ca. 1940 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous handwritten prayers, 1895-1970 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Unidentified; Kit and Dan, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Rain barrel at Nancy Wallace, Flint, June 1967, home of Margaret Bright-Holmes, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Bay Tree, Binford - Dora and Gladys; garden at Nancy Wallace (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Dining at the Little Thatch along the Portsmouth Road outside Guilford; unidentified, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - John & Marjorie & Soot; garden at Bramley Grange, June 1967 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Fred Strong McCormick's Creek State Park, Spencer, Indiana, May 1967, unidentified (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Susan, Robert, Beverly, Miss Bess, Beth, Joanne; Willie Ada, 1965-1967 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Nov. 1965; unidentified; Xmas dinner, 1967, at Olive's (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Narissa Strong, Dec. 1967, Unidentified; N.Y.C. on route to Detroit, Sept. 27, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Unidentified; Dec. 1965, Irene Englin, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Joanne, Mother, & Margaret, 1965, unidentified, [ca. 1960s] (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Sept. 1965 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Aug. 1964; Nov. 1968 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Unidentified, 1968 and [ca. 1960s] (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Unidentified, [ca. 1960s] (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Unidentified, Nov. 7, 1961, Phyllis' 33d b'day, Weeki Wachee, [ca. 1960s] (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Unidentified, [ca. 1960s] (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Miss Lil, 1965, unidentified, [ca. 1960s] (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Unidentified, [ca. 1960s] (Box 1, Folder 60-63)
  - Unidentified; Dec. 1967, [home of] Eva Rosin, Santa Barbara, CA (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Aug. 1964; Pamela Mary [Morton?], christened July 8, 1956, Grace Church, Jersey City, NJ; unidentified (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Unidentified; Christmas; July 29, 1953, Queen Mary, New York (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - In the village, Old Bayhill, Aug. 6th, Ursula's dog [Misty?]; Nov. 1965; Frankie, 2-1/2 mo. (Box 1, Folder 67)
- Papers (Box 2, Oversize, Folder 1-15)
  Included among the papers in the Griffiths Collection are materials belonging to Griffiths' roommate Katherine Dick, who may have been associated with the Harris County School for Girls, and a manuscript which may have been written by Bessie Griffiths.
  - Programs: Houston Symphony Orchestra, 1916-1931 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Programs: Miscellaneous, 1916-1930 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Programs: Miscellaneous, 1930-1940, and undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Programs: Bessie Griffiths, 1913-1924, and undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1931 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Receipts: Bessie Griffiths, 1929-1931, and undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Clubs and organizations, 1917-1925, and undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Travel mementos, ca. 1920, and undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1918, and undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Financial documents: Katherine Dick, 1915-1925, and undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - School workbook: Katherine Dick, October 1909 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Katherine Dick, 1917-1930, and undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Manuscript, ca. 1935 (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
  - Passport, June 12, 1916 (Box Oversize)
  - Diploma, July 25, 1919 (Box Oversize)
- Memorabilia (Box 2, Folder 16 (Env. 1)-19 (Env. 10))
  This small section contains a few pieces of jewelry, ticket stubs, dance cards, flag and program.
  - Brass ring, ca. 1920 (Box 2, Folder 16 (Env. 1))
  - Pendants, ca. 1920 (Box 2, Folder 16 (Env. 2-3))
  - Photographic plate for reproduction, Bessie Griffiths, ca. 1920s (Box 2, Folder 17 (Env. 4))
  - Dance cards (2), May 4, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 18 (Env. 5))
  - Tickets (3), Feb. 22, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 18 (Env. 6))
  - Ticket, Galveston Houston Electric Railway Company, March 1917 (Box 2, Folder 18 (Env. 7))
  - Commencement program, Prairie View State College, May 21, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 19 (Env. 8))
  - Flag, ca. 1940 (Box 2, Folder 19 (Env. 9))
  - Hat pin, German, ca. 1915 (Box 2, Folder 19 (Env. 10))